We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
What’s the best way to protect one
of our most important senses?
We start with the story of two
very important plant pigments
that help guard against age-
related macular degeneration.
Anyone who has ever got a sunburn knows
how damaging the UV rays
in sunlight can be.
Imagine what those rays are doing
to the back of our eyeballs,
our retinas?
The eye’s designed to take
sunlight and focus it
like a magnifying glass
into the back of our eyes.
Thankfully we have a layer
of cells in our eye
called the retinal pigment epithelium
that supports and protects our
delicate retinal eyesight machinery.
This layer builds up yellow plant pigments
from our diet, like zeaxantin,
which absorbs blue light and protects
the retina from photo-oxidative damage.
The yellowing of our corneas
when we get cataracts
may actually be our bodies’ defense
mechanism to protect our retinas.
In fact when we go and surgically
remove those cataracts,
our risk of blindness from macular
degeneration shoots up
since we’ve removed that protection.
Instead of trading one type
of vision loss for another,
instead of pigmenting the front
of our eye with cataracts,
better to pigment the back
of eyes with diet.
The pigment in the back of our eye
is entirely of dietary origin,
thus suggesting that
the most common cause
of going blind in the Western
world could be delayed
or even averted with appropriate
dietary modification.
Where in our diet do we get it?
Well, the egg industry brags
that eggs are a good source,
but have an egg nearly day, six
eggs a week for three months,
and the pigmentation in
our eyes barely moves.
And these were the high lutein,
free range, certified organic eggs,
not purchased at the supermarket,
but from a local farm.
Instead of getting phytonutrients
from the egg that came from the chicken
that came from the corn and
blades of grass you pecked on,
what about getting it from the source:
a cup of corn and a half cup
of spinach a day for three months?
A dramatic boost in
protective eye pigment.
What’s also so neat about
this study is that it went back
and measured the levels three
months after the study stopped,
and the levels were still way up here.
So once we build our
macular pigment up
with a healthy diet, our eyeballs
really try to hold on to it.
So even if we go on vacation
and end up eating more
iceberg lettuce than spinach,
our eyes will hold out until we get back.
Yes, eyes can increase zeaxantin
levels in the blood,
but they also raise bad cholesterol
levels and risk of heart disease,
therefore an egg yolk based
dietary strategy
to increase plasma zeaxantin
cannot be recommended.
An alternative, you know, a cholesterol-free
food source is desirable,
like goji berries for example, which have
up to 60 times more zeaxantin than eggs.
A modest dose markedly
increases levels in our body.
An inexpensive, effective, safe,
whole foods strategy
to increase the zeaxantin
in our blood stream.
But we don't need it in our blood.
We need it in our eyes.
So how about a double-blind randomized
placebo-controlled trial?
To preserve eyesight in the elderly
in traditional Chinese medicine,
people are often prescribed
40 to 100 goji berries a day.
But here they just used 15 berries
a day for three months.
But still found it could
protect against loss of pigment
and prevent the buildup of
what’s called soft drusen,
which is just debris that builds up
in the back of our eye,
both of which are associated with
age-related macular degeneration,
the leading cause of legal blindness
in older men and women,
affecting more than 10 million Americans.
Now note they gave the berries
with milk in this study,
so the butterfat could increase
the absorption of the carotenoid pigments.
A healthier way to get the same effect
would be to just eat goji berries
with nuts or seeds, in other
words, Goji trail mix.
In our next story,
kale and collard greens
play a starring role
in the prevention of glaucoma.
Glaucoma is the
second leading cause
of legal blindness
in white women,
but the #1 cause of blindness
in African-American women.
That's one reason researchers
chose a population
of African-American women
to study the effects
of fruit and vegetable consumption
on glaucoma risk,
but the other reason
is because they were
specifically interested in foods
with the highest concentration
of those eye-protecting
phytonutrients like zeaxanthin--
kale and collard greens—
— but you'd be lucky if you
could find 1 in 10 white people
eating even a single
serving a month,
whereas that was a no-brainer
for African Americans.
What'd they find?
Well, as I've stressed
over the years,
all fruits and vegetables
are not the same.
Whether you ever
ate bananas
or had one or more
bananas every day
didn't seem to
matter much,
but eating a couple
oranges every week
was associated with
dramatically lower risk.
Not orange juice, though,
you can drink orange juice
every day and it
didn't seem to matter.
A similar finding with peaches.
Fresh peaches seemed to work
but canned peaches didn't.
Similarly vegetables in
general as a catch-all term
didn't seem to matter.
For example, whether you ate
a green salad twice a week,
once a week or
zero times a week
didn't seem to matter
when it came to
reducing glaucoma risk–
But you know how pitiful
most people's salads are.
White people, take note,
as you may need it even more.
The lighter our eye color,
the more greens we need to eat.
Blue eyes let 100 times
more light through,
so people with blue
or gray eyes appear
significantly more
vulnerable to damage
compared to brown or black,
with green and hazel
somewhere in the middle.
It's interesting - carrots
appeared to be less protective
in black women compared
to white women.
They suggest it could
be a difference
in food preparation methods.
Perhaps the African
American subjects
tended to eat
carrots raw,
limiting the absorption
of certain nutrients,
while they chopped and prepared
their collard greens
with oil making the nutrients
more bioavailable,
because the absorption of
carotenoid phytonutrients
depends on the
presence of fat,
which is why I encourage
people to eat nuts or seeds
with their greens—a little
tahini sauce or something.
Why not just take a
zeaxanthin pill?
Well, we don't know
what exactly is in
these wonderful foods that's
working their wonders
so it may be better to just
recommend folks eat them,
rather than supplements.
And in fact, people that take
calcium or iron supplements
may be doubling, quadrupling,
or septupling
their odds of glaucoma.
Better to just get
most of our nutrients
from produce, not pills.
Finally today,
we look at the best dietary
treatments for eye strain.
What happens to our eyesight if we sit
in front of a computer all day?
In previous years "the rapid spread of
computers in the home and workplace
has led to an increase in
ocular and visual problems,
including eye discomfort, blurring of distant
objects, eye strain, and visual fatigue,"
so called nearwork-induced transient myopia.
That's when, after staring at
a computer screen for a while,
you look out the window and
things start out all blurry.
That's because our poor little ciliary
muscles pulling at the lenses in our eyes
are locked in this constant state of
contraction to keep that near focus.
Over time this can have
long-term adverse consequences.
Yes, we could waste
4 to 12 minutes an hour
taking breaks staring out the window,
but what if you've got
nutrition videos to make?
The effects of black currant
intake on video display terminal
work-induced transient refractive
alteration in healthy humans.
A double-blind placebo-controlled
crossover study
finding a significant improvement
in refractive values
and eye strain symptoms
compared to placebo.
Note what passes for currants in the U.S.
are actually champagne grape raisins,
not actual black currants,
which were banned in the U.S.
a century ago at the behest
of the lumber industry
for fear that they might spread a plant
disease that affects white pine,
which we hardly even harvest any more.
They are, however, currant-ly [cough]
are making a comeback,
though any anthocyanin-rich berry
might have similar benefits.
For example, there was a previous
study done on bilberries.
Why didn't I report on it
when it came out?
Because I can't read Japanese.
Why not just take
bilberry powder capsules?
Because, as we've seen over and over,
when you test supplements
you're lucky if they have
any of what it says on the label.
Furthermore, for products actually
containing bilberries at all,
labeling was often uninformative,
misleading or both,
something the herbal supplement
market is infamous for.
The largest study to date found
that it appears most herbal
supplement labels lie.
And who wouldn't want to eat this,
rather than this?
It's interesting — bilberries gained
notoriety during World War II
when it was said that pilots
in the British Royal Air Force
were eating bilberry jam
to improve their night vision.
Turns out this may have been a story
concocted to fool the Germans.
The real reason the Brits were able
to all the sudden target Nazi bombers
in the middle of the night before
they even made it to the English Channel
was likely not because of bilberries,
but because of a top secret new invention
they needed to keep quiet, called radar.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.